Guide to the Camp Midvale / Nature Friends of America Oral History Collection OH.015
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Camp Midvale/Nature Friends of America Oral History Collection
1987-1988
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Lanset, Andy
OH.015
2.25 Linear Feet In 1 manuscript box, 1 compact disk box, 3 card catalog drawers.
Camp Midvale, located near Ringwood, New Jersey, was purchased by the Nature Friends of America in 1930. The U.S. branch of this organization was founded by German-American socialists and trade unionists in 1910 to provide workers with outdoor recreational opportunities. Interviewees describe life at the camp, hiking and other activities, the immigrant experience, and political activities. The collection's thirty-five interviews were conducted by Andy Lanset and were used to create the radio documentary "Camp Midvale: An Oral History," which is also included in the collection. Indexes are available for many interviews.
Access Restrictions
Content open to users without restriction. Entire collection has been digitized. Researchers must use access compact disks.
Historical/Biographical Note
Camp Midvale, located in Ringwood, New Jersey, was one of 400 camps worldwide established by the Nature Friends, whose U.S. branch had been founded in 1910 by German-American socialists and trade unionists. The organization's goals were to preserve wildlife and to provide workers with affordable outdoor recreation. Camp Midvale's 150 acres, with a clubhouse and hiking trails, was purchased in 1930 and served as a hub for Nature Friends' activities on the East Coast.
Nature Friends offered a political perspective, combining ecological "nature love" with progressive sympathies. "Fascist convictions" were outlawed in their by-laws. Hikers raised funds for such causes as the Scottsboro Boys, the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, the Committee for the Protection of the Foreign Born, the Committee to Release the Rosenbergs, and the civil rights movement. Placed on the Attorney General's list of subversive organizations in 1947, Nature Friends saw its members severely harassed. Camp Midvale was given to the Ethical Culture Society in 1968 in hope that it would be preserved as an ecological retreat.
Camp Midvale, located in Ringwood, New Jersey, was one of 400 camps worldwide established by the Nature Friends whose U.S. branch had been founded in 1910 by German-American socialists and trade unionists. The organization's goals were to preserve wildlife and to provide workers with affordable outdoor recreation. Camp Midvale's 150 acres, with a clubhouse and hiking trails, was purchased in 1930 and served as a hub for Nature Friends' activities on the East Coast.
Nature Friends offered a political perspective, combining ecological "nature love" with progressive sympathies. "Fascist convictions" were outlawed in their by-laws. Hikers raised funds for such causes as the "Scottsboro Boys", the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, the Committee for the Protection of the Foreign Born, the Committee to Release the Rosenbergs, and the civil rights movement. Placed on the Attorney General's list of "subversive organizations" in 1947, Nature Friends saw its members severely harassed. Camp Midvale was given to the Ethical Culture Society in 1968 in hope that it would be preserved as an ecological retreat.
Arrangement
Collection arranged alphabetically by interviewee surname.
Scope and Contents note
Oral history interviews conducted by Andy Lanset, freelance radio producer and oral historian, with funding from the New Jersey Historical Commission in 1987 and 1988. Interviews document the scope of Nature Friends' activities. The resulting one hour documentary program was broadcast on WBAI, WFMU, WFUV in 1988, entitiled "Camp Midvale: An Oral History", which is also included. All interviews are open for research and many have indexes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Andy Lanset.
Related Archival Materials
Another collection, Camp Midvale/Nature Friends of America: FOIA Files (TAM.089), contains documents of FBI investigations into the activities of the camp, Nature Friends Incorporated, The Labor Lyceum and other related organizations, obtained through a Freedom of Information Act request.
Ecology movement |z United States; Working class |x Recreation |z United States; Radicalism -- United States.; Camps |z New Jersey.; Socialism -- United States.; Socialism and youth -- United States.; Camp Midvale (Ringwood, N.J.)
- Camp Midvale: An Oral History radio program, Oct 3, 1988 (Box 3, Cassette 1A-1B, Box 2, Cd Camp Midavle: An Oral History 1-2)
- Theresa & Irwin Adametz, Jun 20, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 2A, Box 1, Folder 1, Box 2, Cd Adametz 1)
- Norma Allen, Dec 11, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 3A, Box 1, Folder 2, Box 2, Cd Allen 1)
- Bertha Bloksberg, Aug 4, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 3, Box 2, Cd Bloksberg 1-2, Box 3, Cassette 4A)
- Esther & Fred Buchthal, Oct 11, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 5A, Box 2, Cd Buchtal 1, Box 1, Folder 4)
- August Danielsson, Aug 15, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5, Box 2, Cd A. Danielsson 1, Box 3, Cassette 6A)
- Claire Danielsson, Aug 15, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 7A, Box 2, Cd C. Danielsson 1, Box 1, Folder 6)
- Hanni Duffy, Nov 15, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 8A, Box 2, Cd Duffy 1)
- Robert & Kornelia Ehrlich, Jun 6, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 9A, Box 2, Cd R. & K. Erlich 1-2, Box 1, Folder 7)
- Saul Ehrlich, Nov 8, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8, Box 2, Cd S. Erlich 1, Box 3, Cassette 10A)
- Max & Estelle Halle, Dec 30, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9, Box 3, Cassette 11A, Box 2, Cd Halle 1)
- Al & Judy Hodges, Aug 7, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 10, Box 3, Cassette 12A, Box 2, Cd Hodges 1)
- Werner Jurow, May 12, 1988 (Box 2, Cd Jurow 1-2, Box 3, Cassette 13A-13B)
- Otto & Lillian Karsch, Dec 10, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 14A-14B, Box 2, Cd Karsch 1-3, Box 1, Folder 11)
- Carl Kirschner, Jan 21, 1988 (Box 2, Cd C. Kirschner 1, Box 3, Cassette 15A, Box 1, Folder 12)
- Ethyl Kirschner, Dec 19, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 13, Box 3, Cassette 16A, Box 2, Cd E. Kirschner 1-2)
- George Kirschner, Nov 7, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14, Box 2, Cd G. Kirschner 1-3, Box 3, Cassette 17A-17B)
- Leon Kuhl, Aug 29, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 18A, Box 2, Cd Kuhl 1-2)
- Meyer Kukle, Jul 9, 1987 (Box 2, Cd Kukle 1-2, Box 3, Cassette 19A, Box 1, Folder 15)
- George Levine, Sep 17, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 20A, Box 2, Cd Levine 1, Box 1, Folder 16)
- Virginia Marson, Jul 11, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 21A, Box 2, Cd Marson 1, Box 1, Folder 17)
- Louis Merkel, Jul 10, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 22A, Box 2, Cd Merkel 1, Box 1, Folder 18)
- Benaldo Montenegro & Rose, Aug 29, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 23A-23B, Box 2, Cd Montenegro 1-3, Box 1, Folder 19)
- George Nieswand, Jan 21, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 20, Box 3, Cassette 24A, Box 2, Cd Nieswand 1)
- Elsa Powitz, Jun 14, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 21, Box 2, Cd Powitz 1, Box 3, Cassette 25A)
- Harry Rabinowitz, Aug 22, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 22, Box 2, Cd Rabinowitz 1-2, Box 3, Cassette 26A-26B)
- Reinhard Richter, Jun 19, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 23, Box 3, Cassette 27A, Box 2, Cd Richter 1)
- Fritz Schmucker, undated (Box 3, Cassette 34B, Box 2, Cd Schmucker 1-2, Box 1, Folder 30)
- Edith Segal, Jun 23, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 28A, Box 1, Folder 24, Box 2, Cd Segel 1-2)
- Emanuel Sterne, Jun 6, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 29A, Box 1, Folder 25, Box 2, Cd Sterne 1)
- Louis Sutherland, Aug 20, 1987 (Box 2, Cd Sutherland 1, Box 3, Cassette 30A, Box 1, Folder 26)
- Walter Tanzer, Aug 25, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 31A, Box 2, Cd Tanzer 1, Box 1, Folder 27)
- Sonia Vieth, Jul 11, 1987 (Box 3, Cassette 32A, Box 1, Folder 28, Box 2, Cd Vieth 1)
- William Voelkel, Jun 27, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 29, Box 2, Cd Voelkel 1, Box 3, Cassette 33A)
- Hans Wittich, Dec 28, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 30, Box 2, Cd Wittich 1-5, Box 3, Cassette 34A-C)
- Hans Wittich, Gerhardt Zwilling & Henrietta Zwilling, Dec 28, 1987 (Box 2, Cd Zwilling & Wittich 1-3, Box 3, Cassette 35A-B, Box 1, Folder 31)